

Ananthmanoj Nayak Data Scientist

manojnayak1996@gmail.com

+91 9483099231

Bangalore, India

. 3.0

linkedin.com/in/amnayak

Machine Learning Enthusiast, having around 6+ years of technical experience in **Neural Networks**, and creating **Data Regression models**. Strong academic exposure to Data Science with End to End Industry relevant use cases. An action-oriented tech geek eager to explore and be productive.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Data Scientist

Net Connect Globals

12/2024 - Present

Bangalore, Ind

Tasks

- Developed a machine learning model to predict customer churn for client data using historical transaction and engagement data.
- Built a machine learning model using XGBoost, Random Forest, and Logistic Regression, improving churn prediction accuracy by 94%.
- Engineered key features using RFM analysis and integrated SQL for efficient data processing.
- Tools: Colab, Jupyter, SQL, Python, Git, Classification Model

Data Scientist

iElektron Technologies Pvt Ltd

11/2021 - 12/2024 Bengalore, Ind

3.5 Years of experience in designing, training, and deploying Computer Vision and Multi-Modal ML models for Advanced Driver Assistance Systems (ADAS)

Tacks

- Engineered EfficientNet-B3 and LSTM-based models for real-time driver behavior analysis, achieving 85% precision & reducing false alerts by 25% through multi-modal fusion of video feeds & vehicle telemetry for Mercedes Benz Research & developement India.
- Integrated MediaPipe Face Mesh for facial landmark detection (468 points) and head pose estimation, resolving occlusion challenges with IR camera compatibility
- Designed a CNN-XGBOOST hybrid architecture to analyze temporal driver activities, leveraging tensorflow and SciPy to process 10k+ records with 92% recall on edge cases.
- Experience in solving real-world business problems by working with global cross functional team, leveraging machine learning and deep learning techniques on large data sets.
- Tools: Pycharm, AWS, GIT, Python, Sql, Machine Learning Models

Data AnalystWipro Ltd

02/2018 - 11/2021 Bangalore, Ind

3+ years' experience as Project Engineer then promoted to Data Migration Expert in **Data Analysis and Artificial Intelligence domain.**

Tasks

- Having the responsibility to extract the data from the client's system, analyze and extract the features depending on business needs and upload the data to the updated server.
- Translated business objectives into an analytical approach and identified data sources to support analysis.
- Also experienced in working with SQL\ MySQL and **ETL tools.**
- Internal Projects / Freelancing:
- Recipe Recommendation System, to recommend the dishes from the user given set of recipes and help them cook the recipe.
- Tools: Syniti ETL tools, Python, SQL

SKILLS

Machine Learning:

supervised learning, unsupervised learning,K-Nearest Neighbors, Random Forest, Ensemble Techniques, Decision Tree, Naïve Bayes, SVC, SVM

Deep Learning

Neural Network (ANNs), Convolutiona Neural Network (CNNs), Long-Short Term Memory (LSTMs), DNN

Libraries:

Pandas, SciPy, Numpy, Scikit-learn, NLTK, Keras

Statistical Analysis:

Predictive Analysis, Principal Componen Analysis, Dimensionality Reduction, Exploratory Analysis

Data Visualization:

Tableau, Matplotlib, Seaborn, OpenCV, MS Excel

Programming Language:

Python, C++, Shell

Database Language:

SOL MySOL Oracle MongoDE

EDUCATION

Masters in Data Science (02/2024)

Deakins University, associated with Great Learnings

Post Graduate in Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning (10/2020)

University of Texas at Austin, associated with Great Learning

Bachelor of Engineering - Computer Science and Engineering (05/2018)

Visvesvaraya Technological University

PROJECTS

RECIPE RECOMMENDATION SYSTEM (05/2021)

- To recommend the dishes from the user given set of recipes and help them cook the
- Developed a recipe recommendation system using natural language processing and machine learning techniques to recommend dishes based on user-provided recipe ingredients and preferences.
- Implemented collaborative filtering and content-based filtering methods to generate personalized recipe recommendations.
- Optimized the recommendation algorithm to improve its performance and reduce the computation time.

PNEUMONIA DETECTION SYSTEM. (09/2020)

- The goal is to build a pneumonia detection system, assisting physicians to make better clinical decisions or even replace human judgement in certain functional areas of healthcare.
- Aim is to locate the position of inflammation in an image. Handling the data with generators and using the transfer learning technique to build the Mask RCNN and ResNet Neural Network model solved the problem. Used techniques of Computer Vision to locate the position of the inflammation.
- The developed model was about 94.8% percent accuracy score, 85% mean_iou, and a loss of 10%.

FACE RECOGNITION WITH INTERACTION SYSTEM (07/2020)

- The objective of this project is to build a face recognition system, which **detects** and recognizes faces. Along with an interactive system that interacts by dialogues accordingly.
- Used techniques of Siamese Networks and Keras for recognition of the face, CNN to locate the position of the face. Used Text to Speech for and NLP algorithms to make the program talk and convert the user input voice to text.
- The developed model was about **96.07% accuracy score**.

AWARDS & RECOGNITION

Bravo Award (2022)

Awarded with Bravo award for best performance and support

Star Of The Month June (2021)
Rewarded for the work performance given in the month of July

DAAI Circle of Excellence (2020)

It is been rewarded in recognition of excellent contribution to the winning team.

Execution Excellence Award (2019)

By Philips Account, Technology BU for the performance exhibited in FY18-19

ED. SUPPORT VOLUNTEER (2018)

Volunteered at Make A Difference, a non-profit Org